Utica Trades Assembly Records 5278
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Utica Trades Assembly Records
1880-1932
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Utica Trades Assembly
5278
7 cubic feet
7 linear ft.
Minutes, reports, pamphlets, correspondence, constitutions.
The records include Utica Trades Assembly minutes and other administrative records, financial records and correspondence.
3833885
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
CB, October 11, 2012
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, March 10, 2015
Biographical / Historical
The Utica Trades Assembly, also known as the Trades and Labor Assembly of Utica and Vicinity, was a city central of the American Federation of Labor (A.F. of L.) Its activities were directed toward strengthening the Utica locals through mutual support and securing New York State legislation favorable to labor.
Scope and Contents
The minutes (1886-1911 (4 vol.)) reflect the Assembly's activities in both its routine administration and on public issues. These minutes document, for example, the UTA's activities on behalf of a shorter working day (1883-1884, 1906-1907, 1911), its support of state ownership of the railroads and a New York mills strike (1894), and its work on a committee with both the Socialist Labor Party and the Utica Common Council to investigate the possibility of municipal ownership of the city's electric lighting (1895-1896), among other issues.
The minutes volumes also include the minutes (1892-1895) of the UTA's Label Committee which record its concern over the issue of how to deal with local merchants selling "scab"-produced goods.
UTA correspondence (1882-1927) indicates extensive involvement of that organization in local, state and national labor activities. Most numerous are form letters from labor organizations urging national boycotts in support of striking or locked-out workers, usually those involved in disputes over non-recognition of a union. Of interest is an undated appeal from the International Association of Machinists that labor denounce Thomas A. Edison for having fired all union workers at an Edison plant.
UTA response to these national boycotts is indicated by correspondence from businesses in Pennsylvania, Cincinnati and San Francisco involved in the LOS ANGELES TIMES boycott of 1903. The letters are in reply to UTA requests that the companies cancel advertising in the TIMES.
Notable direct correspondence with other labor organizations includes letters from A.F. of L. President Samuel Gompers and Secretary Frank Morrison, ordering the UTA to recognize the local Musicians' Union (July and August, 1902), with the UTA maintaining an independent stance, defending its refusal in a lengthy reply.
The UTA was independent-minded in its dealings with local businesses as well. In 1892, a report from a special UTA committee, appointed to investigate charges against a hardware merchant, found that merchant fair to labor. At the same time, the UTA cooperated with local and regional labor groups by participating in organizing efforts and special events as well as boycotts.
The most significant local boycott call came from the Bakery and Confectionery Workers Utica local, which, in a series of letters from ca.1895 to 1903, described working conditions of non-union bakers, reported on a survey of union-made baked goods in local stores, and asked for a boycott of several large non-union bakeries which were trying to drive out competitors.
In addition to minutes and correspondence, the UTA papers contain the Assembly's financial records for the period 1882-1902 which include bills, financial statements, and dues payment records.
Of particular interest are the records of defunct locals which belonged to the UTA. These include minutes books (2 vol.) (1898-1902), cash books (2 vol.) (1913-1932), and a membership book (1924-1928) of the Journeymen Barbers' International Union, Local 103; minutes books (2 vol.) (1903-1920) of the International Union of United Brewery Workers, Utica local; a minutes book (1914-1918) of the Utica Building Trades Council; minutes books of the Executive Board (4 vol.) (1885-1891), and a minutes book of the Label Committee (1897- 1900) of the Cigar Makers' International Union, No. 7.
Other items of interest include a minutes book (1890-1897) of the International Molders and Allied Workers' Union, Local No. 112; minutes books (4 vols.) (1887-1920) of the Brotherhood of Painters, Decorators, and Paperhangers, Local 69; and a minutes book (1920- 1925) of the Sheet Metal Workers International Association, Local No. 23. Among the events documented in these volumes is a daily record of the month-long strike of Utica painters in 1911.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5288: International Brotherhood Pulp, Sulphite, Paper Mill Workers, Local 670 (Utica, NY) Minute Book 5811: International Typographical Union Local 62 (Utica, NY) Minute Book 6046: Archives Union File (AUF)
Boycott -- Bakers and bakeries -- New York (State) -- Utica; Painters' Strike, Utica, N.Y., 1911.; Public utilities -- New York (State) -- Utica; Labor unions -- Political activity -- New York (State) -- Utica; Trade-union label -- United States; Bakery employees.; Cigar makers.; Lobbyists.; Los Angeles Boycott, 1903.; Union labels -- United States; Bakery employees -- Labor unions -- New York (State) -- Utica; Labor unions -- New York (State) -- Congresses; Labor unions -- New York (State) -- Local unions; Labor unions -- New York (State) -- Utica; Painters, Industrial -- Labor unions -- New York (State) -- Utica; Tobacco workers -- Labor unions -- New York (State) -- Utica; Bakery and Confectionery Workers' International Union of America; Brotherhood of Painters, Decorators, and Paperhangers of America. Local 69 (Utica, N.Y.); Cigar Makers' International Union of America. Local 7 (Utica, N.Y.); International Molders and Allied Workers' Union; International Molders and Allied Workers' Union. Local 112 (Utica, N.Y.); International Union of United Brewery, Flour, Cereal, Soft Drink, and Distillery Workers of America. Utica Local; Journeymen Barbers' International union of America; Journeymen Barbers' International Union of America. Local 103 (Utica, N.Y.); Los Angeles Times; New York State Federation of Labor; New York State Trades Assembly; Sheet Metal Workers' International Association; Sheet Metal Workers' International Association. Local 23 (Utica, N.Y.); Socialist Labor Party; Utica Building Trades Council; Utica Trades Assembly; Workingmen's Federation of the State of New York; Bates, E. A.; Edison, Thomas A. (Thomas Alva), 1847-1931; Gompers, Samuel, 1850-1924; Horton, E. B.; Morrison, Frank, 1859-1949; Rosenthal, Alex
3833885
- I. Utica Trades Assembly - A. Administrative records: Minutes 1886-1898 (Box 1)
  - Minutes, 1886-1890 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Bound volume (Bd. v.)
  - Minutes, 1883-1898 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1891-1898 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Bound volume
- I. Utica Trades Assembly - A. Administrative Records: Minutes 1898-1911 (Box 2)
  - Minutes, 1898-1904 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1902 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1903 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1904-1906 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1905-1911 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- I. Utica Trades Assembly - A. Administrative Records: Constitution, Amendments-Miscellaneous Committee Records (Box 3)
  - Constitution, Amendments (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Resolutions (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Resolutions (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Credentials (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Credentials (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Credentials (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Credentials (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Credentials (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Credentials (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Credentials (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Credentials (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Credentials (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Credentials (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Credentials (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Roll Calls (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Officers Reports (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Committee on Organization (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Grievance Committee (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Grievance Committee (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Label Committee (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Legislative Committee Records (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Legislative Committee Records (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Miscellaneous committee Records (Box 3, Folder 23)
- I. Utica Trades Assembly - B. Financial Reports: 1882-1902 (Folders 1-5) II. Correspondence - A. U.T.A. General Correspondence (Folder 6) II. Correspondence - B. Organizational Correspondence: Albany Central Federation of Labor-Button Workers Protective (Box 4)
  - Reports, Financial, 1882-1902 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Reports, Financial, 1882-1902 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Reports, Financial, 1882-1902 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Reports, Financial, 1882-1902 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Reports, Financial, 1882-1902 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - U.T.A. General Correspondence (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Albany Central Federation of Labor (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Amalgamated Association of Street Railway Employees (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Amalgamated Meat Cutters and Butcher Workmen (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Amalgamated Rubber Workers Union of America (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Amalgamated Sheet Metal Workers International Association, Local 211 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Amalgamated Wood-Workers International Union of America (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - American Federation of Labor (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - American Federation of Labor (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - American Federation of Labor, New York State Branch (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - American Railway Union (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Axton-Fisher Tobacco Company (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Bakery and Confectionery Workers International Union of America (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Bakery and Confectionery Workers International Union of America (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Bartenders Union, Number 120 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Bill and Caldwell (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Boil makers and Iron Ship Builders of America (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Boot and Shoe Workers Union (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Brooklyn Hat Finishers Association (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Brooklyn Labor Lyceum Association (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America, Local 125 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Building Trades Section (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Button Workers Protective Union, Number 8789 (Box 4, Folder 28)
- II. Correspondence - B. Organizational Correspondence: California State Federation of Labor-Workingmen's Federation of the State of New York (Box 5)
  - California State Federation of Labor (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Carrara Paints (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Central Federation of Labor of Albany (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Central Labor Council, Cincinnati (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Central Trades and Labor Assembly, Syracuse (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Cigar Makers Union, Number 7 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Clothing Cutters and Trimmers, Number 136 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Coopers' International Union of North America (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Defense Committee, New York City (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - District of Columbia Central Labor Union (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Erie Typographical Union, Number 77 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Federal Labor Unions (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Federal Trade Council, Milwaukee (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Federation of Labor Unions (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Flour Packers and Mailers, Number 6348 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - General Relief Committee, Textile Strikers (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Globe Woolen Company (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Nettie Harrison (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Hoffman Beverage Company (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - International Association of Allied Metal Mechanics (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - International Association of Machinists (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - International Brotherhood of Stationary Firemen, Number 4 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - International Furniture Workers (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Iron Molders Union of North America, New York State Branch (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Journeymen Bakers and Confectionery Union Number 141 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Journeymen Barbers International Union (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Journeymen Stove Cutters Association, Utica Branch (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Labor Union Mutual Legal Aid Society (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Metal Polishers, Buffers, Platers, Brass Molders and Brass Workers, Number 124 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - National Association of Letter Carriers, Branch 375 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - National Non-Partisan Federation (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Nelson and Morris Company (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - New Jersey Federation of Labor (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - New York State Assembly (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - New York State Department of Labor (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - New York State Federation of Labor (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - New York State Publicity Bill Committee (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - New York State Senate (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - New York Stereotypers Union, Number 1 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Oneonta Trade and Labor Council (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Order of Knights of Labor (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Pennsylvania Federation of Labor (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Penfield and Stone (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Retail Clerks International Protective Association (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Rome Trades Assembly (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - San Francisco Labor Council (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Schenectady Trades Assembly (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Sheet Metal Workers International Alliance, Number 211 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Shirt, Waist, and Laundry Workers International Union (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Socialist Trade and Labor Alliance of the United States and Canada (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Springfield Central Labor Union (Box 5, Folder 51)
    51a: Steel Cabinet Workers Union, Number 7294
  - Suspender Makers' Union, Number 9560 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Syracuse Branch, Woodcarvers' Association (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Tackmakers' Union, Number 8557 (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Tanners' Union (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Tobacco Workers International Union (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - Trades Union Label League (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - Triumpha Shoe Polish Company (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - Trunk and Bag Workers International Union, Number 20 (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - Twist and Warp Lace Makers and Warpers, Sidney Branch (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - United Association Journeymen Plumbers, Gas and Steam fitters of the United States and Canada (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - United Cloth Hat and Cap Makers, North America (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - United Garment Workers of America (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - United Hatters of North America (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - United Mine Workers of America (Box 5, Folder 65)
  - "Utica Advocate" (Box 5, Folder 66)
  - Utica Board of Civil Service Examiners (Box 5, Folder 67)
  - Utica Building Trades Council (Box 5, Folder 68)
  - Utica Musical Protective Union, Number 69 (Box 5, Folder 69)
  - Wall Paper Machine Printers' and Color Mixers' Union (Box 5, Folder 70)
  - Watch Case Engravers' International Association of America (Box 5, Folder 71)
  - Westcott and Parker (Box 5, Folder 72)
  - Western Federation of Miners (Box 5, Folder 73)
  - Western Labor Union (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - Wolff Process Leather Company (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - Workers Health Bureau (New York) (Box 5, Folder 76)
  - Workingmen's Assembly, State of New York (Box 5, Folder 77)
  - Workingmen's Federation of the state of New York (Box 5, Folder 78)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 5, Folder 79)
- III. Records of Related Unions - A. Barbers International Union, Local 103 (Box 6)
  - Barbers International Union, Local 103: Minute Book, 1898-1902 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Barbers International Union, Local 103: Minute Book, 1915-1928 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Barbers International Union, Local 103: Cash Book, 1913-1917 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Barbers International Union, Local 103: Cash Book, 1928-1932 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Barbers International Union, Local 103: Membership Book, 1924-1928 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- III. Records of Related Unions - B. Brewery Workers Local Union (Folders 1-2) III. Records of Related Unions - C. Building Trades Council, Utica (Folder 3) (Box 7)
  - Brewery Workers Local Union: Minute Book, 1903-1914 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Brewery Workers Local Union: Minute Book, 1914-1920 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Building Trades Council, Utica: Minute Book, 1914-1918 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- III. Records of Related Unions - D. Cigar Makers Union, Number 7 (Box 8)
  - Cigar Makers Union, Number 7: Minute Book, 1880-1888 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Cigar Makers Union, Number 7: Minute Book, 1891-1895 (Box 8, Folder 2)
- III. Records of Related Unions - D. Cigar Makers Union, Number 7 (continued) (Box 9)
  - Cigar Makers Union, Number 7: Minute Book, 1895-1906 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Cigar Makers Union, Number 7: Minute Book, 1907-1910 (Box 9, Folder 2)
- III. Records of Related Unions - D. Cigar Makers Union, Number 7 (continued) (folders 1-5) III. Records of Related Unions - E. Molders Union, Local Number 112 (folder 6) (Box 10)
  - Cigar Makers Union, Number 7: Minute Book, Executive Board, 1885-1887 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Cigar Makers Union, Number 7: Minute Book, Executive Board, 1887-1889 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Cigar Makers Union, Number 7: Minute Book, Executive Board, 1889-1890 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Cigar Makers Union, Number 7: Minute Book, Executive Board, 1890-1891 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Cigar Makers Union, Number 7: Minute Book, Label Committee, 1897-1900 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Molders Union, Local Number 112: Minute Book, 1890-1897 (Box 10, Folder 6)
- III. Records of Related Unions - F. Painters and Decorators Local 69 (Box 11)
  - Painters and Decorators, Local 69: Minute Book, 1887-1894 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Painters and Decorators, Local 69: Minute Book, 1899-1903 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Painters and Decorators, Local 69: Minute Book, 1904-1912 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Painters and Decorators, Local 69: Minute Book, 1913-1920 (Box 11, Folder 4)
- III. Records of Related Unions - G. Sheet Metal Workers Union, Number 23 Also: Broadsides; Volume entitled "Utica Trades and Labor Assembly" (Box 12)
  - Sheet Metal Workers Union, Number 23: Minute Book, 1920-1925 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Broadsides (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Volume entitled "Utica Trades and Labor Assembly" (Box 12, Folder 3)
- Roll Book (Box 13, Folder 1)